A Guide to the School of Art and Art History Records, c. 1970-2000: UA 0044
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
School of Art and Art History Records,
c. 1970-2000
Special Collections, James Madison University
School of Art and Art History
Tschudi, Alan
Black, Kathy
Ropp, Kevin
UA 0044
.2 cubic feet; 1 box
This collection is comprised of photographs of students and faculty at the School of Art and Art History, now the School of Art, Design and Art History, from c. 1970 to 2000.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Acquisition Information
Items were transferred by Frances Dovel of the School of Art and Art History in 2005.
Arrangement
Items are arranged by subject.
Administrative History
The Art Department in 1970 was based in the Duke Fine Arts Center, which was built in 1967 to house the Art, Theater and Music departments. Due to space constraints, art studios were also located in various spaces around campus: printmaking in the basement of Converse Hall, painting and drawing in a former womn's gymnasuium located in Ashby Hall; sculpture and three-dimensional design in the basement garages at the rear of Harrison Hall. When the school of Music moved to a new facility in 1989, the Art Department occupied more of Duke Hall. Duke Hall housed the Sawhill Gallery, which is currently located on the fourth floor of Warren Hall. Zirkle House, which was demolished in 2006, also housed an art gallery.
In the 1970s, the Art Department was under the Division of the Humanities. The department was reorganized in 1996 as the Department of Art and Art History, and was incorporated into the College of Arts and Letters.
Scope and Content
The collection is comprised of photographs of faculty, students and events related to the Art and Art History Art department, from 1970-2000.
The Art Auctions contain images of Kay and Doug Flory (1:1). Duke Hall contains images of the Sawhill Gallery and slide room (1:2). Named faculty in the collection include: Bonnie Paul, Frances Grove, Ken Szmagaj, Mary Snow, Crystal Theodore, Ken Beer, David Diller, Jerry Coulter, Steve Zaptan, James Crable, Rebecca Humphrey, Kay Arthur, Ron Wyancko, Gary Chatelain, Dick Whitman, Phil James, Barbara Lewis, David Ehrenpreis, Angie To, Karen Gerard, Cole Welter, William Wightman, Corinne Diop, Mark Rooker, Stuart Downs, Masko Miyata, Christina Updike, Sang Yoon, Steve Zapton, Katherine Schwartz, Peter Ratner, Anna Dempsey, Susan Zurbrigg, Barbara Lewis, Richard Hilliard, Bret Hunter, David Haldridge, and Masako Miyata (1:3-6). Named students in the "Student" file include: Karen Byer, Lance Foster, Greg Owens, Karen Harmon, and Phil Ungar. It contains images of Ashby Hall, the Zirkle House Studio, the print shop in the basement of Converse, the slide room, and images of the Sawhill Collection (1:6).
The "Contact Sheets" folder is largely comprised of images of departmental events from 1990-1992, including metals and ceramics students, visiting professor Carol Barton, the David Diller retirement reception, and graduate assistant, Julia Merkel. There are several contact sheets with images of the Ashby studio, textile studio and the Zirkle house from c. 1980s (1:7). The "Miscellaneous" folder contains images of Ron Carrier and Wilson Hall (1:10).
Bibliography
Art And Art History Self Study Report, Box 1, Academic Affairs: Academic Program Reviews, 1976 - present (bulk 1992 - present), UA 0002, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Madison College -- Faculty; James Madison University -- Faculty; Madison College -- Students; James Madison University -- Students; Madison College -- Buildings; James Madison University -- Buildings; Madison College -- History; James Madison University -- History; Education, Higher -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- History; Madison College. Department of Art -- History; James Madison University. School of Art -- History; James Madison University. School of Art and Art History -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
Photographs -- Black and white; Photographs; Color photographs
- Art Auctions, c. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Duke Hall, c. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Faculty Groups, c. 1970 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Faculty and Staff, c. 1970 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Faculty and Student Group, c. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Students, c. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Contact Sheets, 1980-1992 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Publicity Layouts, c. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Visiting Artists and Artwork, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous, c. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)